Okay, so in this video then, we are going
to discuss some of the common roles on a
project and the roles that PMI expect you
to know for the PMP exam.
Now we're going to break up the roles
based on whether it's a traditional
predictive project or whether it's an
Agile project.
First, I'm going to talk
about the roles on a
predictive project or
a traditional project.
Then we'll talk about the roles on an
agile project.
Now, in both cases, though, two roles are
very common.
Stakeholders and the sponsor.
So, stakeholders then.
Stakeholders are anybody that is impacted
by the project.
Anybody that could influence a project in
any way, shape or form, positively,
they would be considered a stakeholder.
The official definition is any individual
group or organization that is positively
or negatively impacted
by the project, or can have
a positive or negative
influence on the project.
So a stakeholder is not just the customer,
nor is it just senior management.
They are stakeholders on the project.
They are key stakeholders on the project.
But there are other projects.
There are other stakeholders on the
project as well, such as yourself.
You as a project manager.
You are a stakeholder of the project
because that project is impacting you.
You're working on that project.
That project is impacting you.
and how you manage
that project is going to
determine success
and failure of the project.
So you are a stakeholder on the project.
Your team members are stakeholders on the
project for the exact same reason.
You've got vendors working on the project.
They would be a stakeholder of the
project.
You've got vendors supplying you with raw
materials.
They would be a stakeholder on the
project.
You've got somebody that could influence a
decision maker on your project.
There would be a stakeholder of the
project.
So any individual, individual group or
organization.
The general public, for example,
if your project is impacting the general
public or the general public
have an influence on your
project, there would be a
stakeholder on the project.
So you're building a road for example,
right?
This road is going through a
neighbourhood.
Well, that neighborhood is going to be
impacted.
And in fact, you know, how that
neighborhood might be negatively impacted
if you're building, say, you know,
big highway, Well, you know, they may
complain and, you
know, that might, the way
they react might actually
shut down the project.
So they're a stakeholder on the project.
So any individual group or organization
that is either positively or negatively
impacted or could have some
kind of positive or negative
influence on the project would
be considered a stakeholder.
Sponsor, right?
Another role, major role for both.
agile and predictive projects is the
sponsor and the sponsor is a person or it
could be a group or individual right it
could be a group or an organization should
i say and they are the ones that are
funding the project so a sponsor is the
one that is funding the project so it
could be an individual that's funding it
or it could be an organization that's
funding it or it could be a group of
people that's funding but they would be
considered the sponsor and the sponsor
then also publishers, issues, signs off on
the project charter.
And there's a separate video on the
project charter.
Now, roles then on a traditional project,
right?
Traditional then meaning predictive
projects.
You have the project manager.
Actually, before we talk about the project
manager, let me start again.
You have the project team, the project
team.
And the project team is basically anybody
and everybody involved on the project.
project, right?
So anybody, so you are part of the project
team, you're the project manager,
you're part of the project team,
right, anybody making a decision on the
project, anybody doing
any work on the project,
they would be part of the project team.
Then you have the project management team,
who is a subset, right, they're a subset
of the project team, right, also known as
a project leadership team, and they are
the key stakeholders that sign of
responsibility.
The key stakeholders that
make strategic decisions about
the project, so they have
sign-off responsibility there.
And then you have the
project manager, and the project
manager is basically
accountable for the entire project.
They are the command and control project
manager.
They collaborate with stakeholders to get
the results, right?
They're responsible for planning.
They're basically accountable for the
entire project.
So that's on a traditional project.
They are the command and control project
manager.
Now the functional manager, now the
functional manager really does not have a
true role on the project, but it's a
functional manager that's providing team
members, providing resources, providing
team members to the project.
So typical in a matrix organization,
you have a person, right, a team member
who is reporting to a functional
manager, but then that team
member might be also be working
on a couple of different projects.
So their functional manager is releasing
that team member to work on the project.
So the project manager then needs to
negotiate with the functional manager so
that they can release that team member
onto the project.
And then you have the business analyst,
the role of the business analyst,
and the rule of the business analyst
really is to collect requirements.
So they understand the requirements,
right?
So they work with the business,
they work with the customer to get the
requirements and then translate those into
something that the technical
teams can understand.
So business analysts play a very important
part and they usually, you know,
often they bridge the gap between the
business, the customer
and the technical teams.
Now, those are roles on a traditional
project.
Now let's talk about the roles on an Agile
project, the major
roles on an Agile project.
So first up, the team
facilitator, also known
as a Scrum Master, It's
a scrum project, right?
There are many different, or there are at
least a few different agile methodologies.
Scrum is just one of them.
That's really the one that you need to
know for the PMP exam.
So the scrum master is known as a team
facilitator.
Now, the team facilitator, they're the
closest thing to a project manager,
the closest role to a project manager.
But they are not a command and control
project manager.
They're what's known as a servant leader.
and a servant leader then encourages
collaboration between team members.
A servant leader will not be delegating
tasks.
In a traditional project, the project
manager is delegating tasks.
In an agile environment, it's a team that
determines what tasks need to be done.
The team facilitators making sure that the
team has all of the tools and
documentation and everything that they
need to do the work, right?
And plus, they're removing
any impediments, any
issues, so that the team
can perform the work.
That is a role of a team facilitator.
So they're still a manager, they're still
leading the team, right?
But whereas the team themselves
are making decisions about the
work that needs to be done,
the team facilitator is making sure
they have all the tools
to make that decision.
They have all the documents to make that
decision, right?
They're not doing any unproductive work,
right?
Non-value-added work, right?
They're removing any of these kind of
impediments or issues or blockers that
could either prevent them from doing the
work or slow them down.
Then you have the product owner, who
is basically the voice of the customer.
They represent the customer.
Right, so they are the ones that are
prioritizing user stories.
So in an agile environment, right, you
get your requirements from the customer.
Those requirements are known as user
stories.
You collect those user stories.
They need to be prioritized to create the
product backlog.
And that's what the
product owner is responsible
for, creating the product backlog, right?
Basically, prioritizing those user
stories.
And then at the end of a sprint,
during the sprint review meeting,
right, then the product owner is going to
be approving those items, right?
that the team is delivering.
Then you have the Agile Team.
Now, the Agile Team is a self-organizing
team.
And in the Agile world, the team is
responsible for the leadership of the project.
In a traditional project
environment, predictive project, the
project manager is the command
and control project manager.
They are responsible for the leadership.
But in an agile
environment, It's the agile
team that is responsible
for the leadership.
They're what's known as a self-organizing
team.
And traditionally, in an agile
environment, you have small teams, right?
Generally, you know, up to about 12
people, generally small teams.
And those teams then are going to include
developers, testers, business analysts,
designers, and, you know, any other role
that's required.
And they have what's known as
cross-functional skills or T-shaped skills.
One of the key aspects
of the Agile team is
everybody has what's
known as T-shaped skills.
And T-shaped skills are discussed in a
separate video, but very briefly,
I mean literally T-shaped, very briefly
means that they have depths of
information, depths of
experience in one technical area,
but then they can diversify
into other areas as well.
They still have skill sets that they could
utilize and leverage in other areas.
So as a very simple example, a developer
can also do testing.
This is a very simple example.
But moreover, the T-shaped skills really
refers to things like management skills,
leadership skills.
So they're technical people,
but they also have these
skill sets in management
and leadership as well.
Because the leadership, or rather the
responsibility of leadership rests with
the project team, the
entire Agile team, not
just the project manager
or the team facilitator.
And so in an agile environment,
the team themselves are determining what
work needs to be done, but there is no
delegation in an agile environment.
The project manager does not delegate the
task, right?
The team determines what task needs to be
performed.
So the team works in a collaborative
environment.
And then you have the Agile coach,
right?
and the Agile Coach is an optional role,
It's not, you know, you don't see it on
every project.
It's an optional role.
But they are there, as the name suggests,
they're a coach.
Mentor, they're basically mentor and coach
the Agile team.
Now, if the team facilitator
is experienced enough,
then the team facilitator
will be the Agile coach.
Otherwise, the Agile coach could be
external to the, to the Agile team.
Okay, so these are
some of the common roles
then, in both a predictive
and an agile project.